but welcome to another assembly tutorial
we're going to write an actual
functioning program that are similar to
one that you'd find in C or C++ okay so
let's get to it if you just make it go
ahead and make a file call it assembly
one ASM or whatever else you want to
name it so we have our file with the ASM
extension for assembly and so let's set
up our basic template for all of our
assembly program
and usually this is what you have for
any typical assembly program that you
want to write you have your your data
section which is going to include
initialized data and you're going to
have your text section which is going to
include all your actual assembly code
and here you're going to have your
uninitialized variables so these are
four variables and these are four
variables as well and you can put these
arrangement in in however way you please
just so long as you have them and really
if you don't use any uninitialized
variables so you don't need to have one
so let's go ahead and erase it for now
because for this program we're not going
to actually need one okay so now let's
write a simple program that displays
something to the screen but in this case
we're not going to use the system call
and we're not going to use the Linux
system call we're actually going to use
a real C type of function called the
printf if you've done any C programming
you're very well aware of what this is
but it's just a a function for those of
you who don't already know
okay so let's actually define some
things that we're going to be printing
to the screen and first of all we're
going to print out a message so message
and zero so it's good to document stuff
as you go ahead and write stuff because
here this means this is a comment and
the zero is likes having a null at the
end of your message so that when
assembly displays this message it knows
where to stop so this tells it to stop
and ten is for our heritage return so we
return to the next line and this is that
from message that we want to display
okay so yeah that's it so and remember
that our labels are treated as memory
locations okay so now we're inside of
our text section which is our code so we
can actually begin coding what we're
going to do now is do a global main all
this does it tells us that we're going
to have a label called main and what
global does it's a reserved word inside
of the assembly language to have our
symbol here main be able to be available
outside of our immediate program so some
other program later on the road will be
able to find our program and know where
to start
okay so we have our label so let's get
coding first thing we want to do is set
up our stack frame which is push EBP
because we're saving whoever called
main R which is in this case it's going
to be an operating system that's going
to call main we're going to save it's a
base pointer and we're going to create a
new one by doing
okay so this takes the stack pointer
moves it into EBP based on to
effectively creating a new one so that's
step setting up our stack frame and so
now let's destroy your stack frame after
we're done with the function so I'm
going to do
we're going to restore this one that we
say we're going to restore the stack
pointer
and so this is entire this is the entire
function it's like having like having
Lord main and in between the parentheses
here is where our code will go so that's
what's going on now let's go ahead and
call this function or print out the
message to the screen and how we do that
is by saying push what this does is it
remember this is our label up here it
pushes this address so all this does is
translate to something like push let's
say that was a memory address it pushes
a memory address into onto the stack and
now we're going to call printf I forgot
to mention them before we call printf
what we need to be able to make sure
that our program knows where knows that
out we're using a variable that has not
been declared in our program but is
available somewhere else and how we do
that is by saying external printf that's
all
this tells the assembly program that our
printf function is not inside of our our
source code it's available externally
simple enough ok so what we have here is
the creation of the stack destruction of
the stack our function body and we push
the memory address of our message and we
calling the printf function and that's
that's it so we save our file and we go
to the command line and we're going to
say you know list all the file or file
is there so we're going to say nessam
which is net wide assembler a file
format e.l.f output to asm1 that's the
name of the father we're going to be
creating and the input file is going to
be a s m1 ASM okay
and Don's you can see it creates the
file that we are looking for now what
we're getting do now is use GCC the
general C++ compiler and output the
final program this is the output and use
the input as ASM 1.0 and it should
compile successful and as you can see
here this is our actual program and now
we're going to do dots for slash asm1
and if all goes well it should compile
successfully and as we just saw it
actually did display our message in
assembly so all right we have just gone
through a successful simple scene sorry
assembly program and written something
that works in the next tutorial we'll go
in into more depth and show you some
more cool stuff with assembly and then
rate and subscribe
okay thank you I'll see you next time